Finding Aid for Michigan Women In Science records, 1972-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Women In Science records 1972-1976
Michigan Women In Science.
0.5 linear feet
91461 Bimu B29 2
Unit of the University of Michigan Center for Continuing Education of Women established in 1972 to provide a forum for women scientists at the university. History, correspondence, minutes, and subject files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated by the organization (donor no. 7932 ) in 1991.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research, except for one folder containing student evaluations of faculty and staff which has been transferred to the vault. This file is closed until January 1, 2021.
Michigan Women in Science (MWIS), a part of the University of Michigan Center for the Education of Women (formerly the Center for the Continuing Education of Women), was formed in March 1972 "during [a] luncheon meeting of two biophysicists, a biochemist, and an astronomer." (See Box 1, folder: History, handwritten notes) Through the years, the goal of MWIS has remained very much the same as when the group first assembled. It is, simply, to provide a forum for women scientists -- faculty, staff, graduate and undergraduate students, as well as interested non-university women scientists -- who seek to overcome gender bias and make the university environment a place where women scientists can work productively. MWIS has worked for these ends by fighting discriminatory acts against women scientists, initiating studies and surveys of both the profession and the people working in it, providing workshops for women scientists, recruiting high school women for careers in the sciences, and offering counseling services specifically aimed at female undergraduate and graduate students in the sciences. In addition to addressing the professional careers of women scientists, MWIS provides a forum in which women interact with and receive encouragement from each other and share their concerns about family and social lives.
Although limited in quantity, the MWIS collection is useful for studying the role women scientists play at the University of Michigan, as well as the environment in which these women have to work. The strength of the collection lies in the correspondence and in the topical files, although minutes contain useful information and are a valuable means of exploring the genesis of the organization.
The MWIS records consist of four series: History, Correspondence, Minutes, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Michigan Women in Science.; University of Michigan. Center for Continuing Education of Women.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- History
  The History series (1 folder) is made up of handwritten notes, press releases, WIN (Women's Information Network) bulletins, newspaper clippings, and MWIS newsletters from 1972 to 1973. The materials are useful in gaining an overview of the organization's activities since its founding.
  - Miscellaneous, 1 folder (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1972-1981
  The Correspondence series (8 folders) is arranged chronologically, and covers the years 1972-1981. There is correspondence relating to the organization's establishment; an interesting survey of women in science at the University of Michigan undertaken in 1972; the Robert Sterling Clark Grant Project, which brought nationally known women scientists to the University of Michigan to hold seminars and present lectures; and MWIS's concern for the professional status of women scientists. MWIS is not isolated on campus, but rather is very active with many other groups, including the Academic Women's Caucus, the Commission for Women within the Affirmative Action Office, and the Center for the Education of Women, its parent organization. The interaction is reflected in the correspondence between MWIS and these other groups. The correspondence for 1980 and 1981 is very sparse; each folder consists of only one or two items.
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981 (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1972-1976
  The Minutes series (2 folders) is arranged chronologically from 1972 to 1976. The first folder, 1972-1973, contains only minutes, while the second folder also contains the mailings and flyers sent with the minutes.
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1976 (includes minutes and enclosures) (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical series (20 folders) is arranged alphabetically. It contains a great deal of material relating to the Clark Grant and the 1972 survey of University of Michigan graduate and undergraduate women students in the sciences, and also includes graduation statistics of students in the sciences at the University of Michigan in 1970-1971.
  - Graduation statistics for women and men from the sciences, University of Michigan, Winter 1970-Summer 1971 (Box 1)
  - National Organizations for Women in Science
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
  - Opinion Survey, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Public Health, School of: First Annual Report of the Advisory Committee on Affirmative Action for Women, University of Michigan, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Robert Sterling Clark Grant Project, 1973-1976
    - Correspondence
      - 1973-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
    - Seminar Committee (Box 1)
    - Seminar Participants
      - 1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
  - Survey of women students and personnel, University of Michigan, 1972
    - Departments
      - Astronomy (Box 1)
      - Biochemistry (Box 1)
      - Biophysics (Box 1)
      - Internal Medicine (Box 1)
      - Nuclear Engineering (Box 1)
      - Nursing (Box 1)
      - Obstetrics and Gynecology (Box 1)
      - Physics (Box 1)
        (contains student evaluations of faculty and staff)
        This file is closed to research until January 1, 2021; the file has been transferred to the vault.
    - Reports (Box 1)